Clifford Berryman Cartoon Collection P008
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
- Series 4: Politics, 1909-1938
  - Original Number: 15, 1920-08-28; Caption: none Description: "D.C." watches, shocked, as Petersburg walks away with Brownlow (carrying a $10,000 check). Petersburg says, "You've got to pay them a living wage, old man!" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 59, 1928-08-25; Caption: none Description: Herbert Hoover arrives in the District on his presidential campaign tour and says, "My! The old place looks good!" "D.C." has greeted him with a sign reading "Welcome to your city." (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 13, 1929; Caption: none Description: "D.C." holds a notice stating, "Senator Bingham of Connecticut explains that he employed a tariff expert to sit in committee and make up for his lack of knowledge of tariff affairs." "D.C." comments, "Whoopee! Maybe they'll yet allow me to sit in and advise 'em on D.C. items." (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 62, 1938-10-03; Description: "D.C." deliberates whether to hand a settlement medal to an airplane representing the newly announced Washington Airport at Gravelly Point, or a dove representing the recently concluded Munich Peace Solution. He muses, "It's hard to decide which landed first." (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 8, 1940-1941; Caption: none Description: "D.C." argues with West Virginia Senator Jennings Randolph over a 100 percent gas tax boost. "D.C." says, "It smells like an oil trust!" and Randolph replies, "But I only handled it for Virginia—that is Virginia Jenckes, now a private citizen of Indiana!" (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 66, Caption: none Description: "D.C." tips his hat to George Norris, holding a sign reading "No more lame ducks thanks to Norris Amendment," and states, "George, I take off my hat to you!" (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 68, Caption: none Description: A dejected "D.C." sits on a step, reading a notice that Congress is delaying adjournment to do something for veterans. "D.C." sighs, "Must be grand to have friends like that!" (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 72, Caption: none Description: A hurt "D.C." lies in the street, cradled by Randolph and Overton, after apparently being hit by a truck labeled "Defense Program," which lumbers away. FDR appears on the scene with an ambulance, and "D.C." says, "You're just in time, Doctor." (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Original Number: 86, 1917-03; Caption: Will it come to this? Description: Many Congressmen fly to work at the Capitol Building using personal sets of wings strapped to their backs. They comment on how fun flying is and how it will affect their mileage allowances. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Original Number: 96, 1908; Caption: The President has been criticized for leaving the White House so frequently—the above suggestion may solve the problem Description: High up in the clouds, the Berryman bear pilots a bi-wing plane attached to the White House, while the press and Wilkie's fleet, also in planes, follow. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Original Number: 100, Caption: none Description: The Squash Center farmers comment on Bilbo winning the Mississippi primary election. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Series 5: Representation, 1929-1947
  These cartoons address the need for political representation for the District of Columbia. Berryman was a vocal proponent of full political rights for the District, and often lamented unfair conditions that required Washingtonians to pay taxes but denied them voting rights. The theme of "taxation without representation" appears frequently, often depicted as a ball-and-chain burden on his "D.C." character. Berryman often used occasions of national holidays to comment on lack of representation; see also: Series 3: Holidays and Events. Here, the Fourth of July, Flag Day, Election Day, and the anniversary of the Boston Tea Party were days when Berryman called for representation for the District. Cartoons also comment on the political developments and progress in the campaign to gain representation.
  - Original Number: 33?, 1929-07-04; Caption: Independence Day 1929 Description: "D.C." wants representation fireworks, but Uncle Sam hands him voteless sparklers, admonishing, "No, no! You must be satisfied with the silent fireworks!" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 32, 1930-12-16; Caption: none Description: "D.C." holds a statement noting that 157 years after the Boston Tea Party, District citizens are still in the same boat as the colonists were back then. He points to boxes labeled "Taxation without Representation" and says, "Long since overtime to throw this overboard." (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 11, 1932-07-04; Caption: Independence Day 1932 Description: "D.C." holds his voteless sparklers as citizens of states with less population loudly parade by with their suffrage skyrockets and representation fireworks. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 4, 1932-10-12; Caption: Columbus Day, 1932 Description: Gesturing to "D.C." imprisoned in stocks, Columbus asks Uncle Sam, "After 440 years, isn't he old enough to vote?" (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 26, 1932-11-08; Caption: [The Forgotten Man] Description: Uncle Sam reassures "D.C." that he won't be forgotten when it comes to taxes, defense, or law enforcement, but "D.C." replies, "Yeah, but you forget me on election day." (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 33, 1933-04-19; Caption: Paul Revere of 1933 Description: "D.C." is dressed like Revere, riding a horse past Constitution Hall--where the 42nd Congress of the Daughters of the American Revolution is meeting--and shouting, "Join in the fight here against taxation without representation!" (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 25, 1933-06-14; Caption: Flag Day 1933 Description: "D.C." gazes at the flag and says, "A beautiful emblem and a joy to look upon—but it means taxation without representation to me!" (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 20, 1933-12-16; Caption: none Description: A old-fashioned figure representing "Young Democrats" incredulously inquires of "D.C.": "You mean to tell me 160 years after the Boston Tea Party you're still taxed but not represented!" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 34, 1934-11-06; Caption: This is Voter's Day for Everyone But—! Description: "D.C." tries to cast a ballot but is turned away by Uncle Sam, who points him to chair labeled "1773 taxation without representation" and says, "You go way back and sit down!" (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 10, 1934-12-16; Caption: Anniversary of the Boston Tea Party Description: ["D.C." reads about women petitioning Congress in favor of District representation and comments, "If the women put on war paint district representation will come in a rush!"] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Original Number: 27, 1936-12-16; Caption: 163d Anniversary of the Boston Tea Party! Description: "Congress" has tossed "D.C." off the ship U.S. and into the ocean, instead of tea boxes labeled "taxation without representation." "D.C." complains, "Hey! It was the tea, not me, to go overboard!" (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Original Number: 3, 1938-04-19; Caption: none Description: Surrounded by news about new taxes, "D.C" looks at a painting of the beginning of the Revolutionary War and says, "That war was never won, if you ask me!" (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Original Number: none, 1938-12-16; Caption: 165th Anniversary of the Boston Tea Party! Description: On the Good Ship Democracy, "D.C." urges President Roosevelt to heave overboard a box labeled "Taxation without representation is poison to democracy." (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Original Number: 6, 1941-03-11; Caption: Wish he would let his left hand know what his right hand is doing Description: A figure representing the House of Representatives signs the "Lend-Lease Bill to help preserve democracy" with one hand while his other hand is clubbing "D.C." (who is holding a sign noting an "unfair income tax") over the head. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Original Number: 7, 1941; Caption: none Description: "D.C." is upset because the Sumners-Capper vote has been postponed again, but the ghost of Abraham Lincoln encourages him to "Keep up the fight—they can't postpone your emancipation forever." (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Original Number: 2, 1946-01-29; Caption: none Description: "D.C." writes a letter to his son, a soldier stationed in occupied Germany, saying he must be proud to be "enforcing the right of all people to vote" but that "D.C." misses him at home in the voteless District. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Original NumberL 5, 1947-05-18; Caption: A Study in Contrasts Description: "D.C." watches with his taxation without representation ball-and-chain while Uncle Sam welcomes newly naturalized citizens, who have full voting rights (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Original Number: 12, Caption: none Description: "D.C." is piloting a vehicle--named Votes for the District--carrying many prominent politicians, while Wilkie and others clamor to hop on as well. Uncle Sam comments, "Everybody's talking about democracy and now someone seems to be doing something about it!" (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Original Number: 28, Caption: Barred! [in pencil] Description: "D.C." cannot vote because the polling place is surrounded by a fence labeled "Keep out!" (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Original Number: 29, Caption: none Description: "D.C." is enthusiastically marching along, carrying the ball-and-chain burden of taxation without representation as well as a sign that reads "Vote November 5 in our own plebiscite." Uncle Sam comments, "I wish all voters had this spirit!" (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Original Number: 30, Date: unknown Caption: Geographical Note: The Potomac River Isolates the American Capital from American Principles Description: "D.C." stands on the banks of the Potomac with his taxation without representation ball-and-chain and watches as the citizens of Arlington County, Virginia, rush to the polls. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Original Number: 31, Caption: none Description: "D.C." holds an American flag and an oversized star labeled "D.C. National Representation" and comments regarding the flag, "That's what it lacks!" (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Series 6: Weather and Nature, 1915-1917
  These cartoons mainly comment on the weather in the District and the changing of the seasons. Berryman often laments the frigid winter, windy spring, and sweltering summer. One of his recurring characters here is a young girl depicting Spring, wearing a large hat covered in flowers. A few cartoons also relate problems of nature in the city, such as flies and starlings.
  - Orignal Number: 92, 1915-03-31; Caption: none Description: The March lion is onstage performing for "D.C." and Uncle Sam, while the April lamb waits in the wings and says, "I'll bet they'll be glad to see my turn." (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 84, 1916-01-10; Caption: The Good Citizens Medal Description: "D.C." pins a medal on the lapel of a man who has been sprinkling sawdust on the icy sidewalks. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 73, 1917-03-22; Caption: none Description: "D.C." greets a young girl representing Spring and pleads, "Now that you're here, please stay." (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 42, 1917-05-12; Caption: The Steadfastness of Fickle May Description: In strong winds, "D.C." reads a weather bulletin calling for "little change in temperature." (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 17, 1930; Caption: none Description: "D.C." is menaced by a flock of starlings while carrying items representing various District problems. He says, "As if I didn't have enough troubles!" (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 38, Caption: The harder it blows the sooner its over Description: Uncle Sam and "D.C." hold onto their hats in gale force winds. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 53, 1920; Caption: No kick on this award [in pencil] Description: "D.C." pins a Distinguished Service medal on a man's lapel because he shoveled the sidewalk and steps in front of his house (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 61, Caption: none Description: A family sits on their porch in coats while the children read advertisement for cool summer getaways. The man says, "Mother, I don't know that going away from here is necessary." (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 71, Caption: none Description: Surrounded by snow, pulling a small express wagon, and holding a little shovel, "D.C." exclaims, "And I've gotten so little help from the sun this winter!" (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 75, 1917-1918; Caption: none Description: "D.C." hugs his furnace for warmth and says, "It might be worse: think of the folks in the war zone." (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Original Number: 82, Caption: none Description: A figure representing July, complete with baggage of heat, humidity, and drought, is being shooed out by "D.C.", who yells, "I won't even shake hands with you! Good riddance!" (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Original Number: 83, 1914-1917; Caption: none Description: Pointing with a fly swatter towards a pile of trash swarming with flies, "D.C." announces, "Forward march! Now's the time for a spring drive!" He also carries a flag reading "Destroy the Fly." (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Original Number: 90, 1910; Caption: A Cry for Help Description: As District citizens struggle through snow banks, "D.C." faces the Capitol building and waves a flag that reads, "Requisition for snow cleaning funds." (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Original Number: 91, 1910; Caption: Only Signs of Spring [in pencil] Description: Two children bundled up in winter clothing gaze at advertisements for spring and summer activities and products. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Original Number: 99, 1910; Caption: The First Day of Spring Description: Sitting in a park, "D.C." greets a young girl representing Spring and chides, "Remember, now, no flarebacks!" (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Original Number: 100, 1910; Caption: Suburbanite's Spring Fever Delirium [in pencil] Description: A man peers over a fence into his neighbor's garden and sees his neighbor with his gardening tools and seed, already surrounded by gigantic vegetables. (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Series 7: World War I, 1917-1919
  Cartoons here depict issues affecting District residents during the first World War, such as fundraising campaigns for government bonds, food shortages, and the return of war heroes.
  - Original Number: 56, 1917-02-16; Caption: none Description: "D.C." goes to put sugar in his drink and is alarmed at the small amount left. A sign reads, "Sugar famine threatened in Washington; supply cut off!" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 40, 1917-05-23; Caption: none Description: "D.C." encourages citizens to buy a Liberty Bond, pointing to the total amount of the District's share and stating, "Let's take the other four millions quickly." (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 49, 1917-06-13; Caption: On the Second Round Description: "D.C." runs around a racetrack marked "D.C.'s Liberty Bond Allotment $8500000" while Uncle Sam and the Berryman bear cheer him on. Uncle Sam comments, "And still going strong!" (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 50, 1917-11-01; Caption: none Description: "D.C." points to announcements showing that participation in the second Liberty Loan campaign has greatly exceeded the total of the first campaign. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 47, 1917-03; Caption: An Annex Needed [in pencil] Description: "D.C." adds an extension to a chart tracking the amount of money raised in the Red Cross campaign drive, as the donations have caused the scale to go off the chart already. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 43, 1919; Caption: none Description: A proud "D.C." stands surrounded by flags proclaiming, "Welcome Home Heroes of Chateau Thierry and Belleau Wood." (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 9, 1917-1918; Caption: none Description: "D.C." holds money, while men run up to him holding war savings stamps. He says, "Help yourselves." (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series 8: World War II, 1940-1945
  This series contains a few cartoons specifically about World War II, which discuss the draft, war loans, and political conferences.
  - Original Number: 18, 1940-10-15; Caption: none Description: Uncle Sam holds the Selective Draft Law and tells "D.C." that everyone should go to the voting places tomorrow to register for the draft. "D.C." replies, "I haven't any voting places but I'll be there all the same." (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 58, 1944-01-18; Caption: none Description: "D.C." prepares to shoot the "4th war loan" apple off Morgenthau's head and reassures him, "Don't be nervous, Henry! I'm good!" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 48a, 1945-12-23; Caption: No Vacant Chairs – If Conferences are to Succeed Description: Bevin, Byrnes and Molotov sit at a conference table reading plans, while an empty chair marked with a cross is highlighted by a spotlight. (Box 8, Folder 3a)
  - Original Number: 48b, 1945-12-23; Caption: No Vacant Chairs – If Conferences are to Succeed Description: Bevin, Byrnes and Molotov sit at a conference table reading plans, while an empty chair marked with a cross is highlighted by a spotlight. (Box 8, Folder 3b)
- Series 9: Artwork, 1934-1948
  This series collects the handful of items in the collection that are not full-sized political cartoons from the Star. It contains Christmas cards, an invitation, a sketch, and printed caricatures, all drawn by Berryman.
  - Stevenson, Thomas P. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Syme, Conrad H. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Somerville, Thomas (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Emmons S. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Spear, Ellis (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Simmons, B. Stanley (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Story, J. P., Jr. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Stone, I. S. (Dr.) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Schwartz, E. P. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Sturtevant, C. L. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Swartzell, G. W. F. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Stone, Charles P. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Smith, Thomas W. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Spier, William E. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Smith, F. H. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Stevens, F. C. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Christmas cards, 1935, 1942, 1943, 1945, 1946, 1948, 1935-1948 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Invitation to University Club dinner, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Sketch of "Albert," undated (Box 9, Folder 19)